בוקר טוב, Boker tov, today we have a new פרק, perek, הריני
נזיר, Hareini Nazir, and let’s give it a go.
So, a lot of the first פרק, perek, as was similar by
נדרים, Nedarim, dealt with questions about different types of language that a
person can use, but particularly unique to נזיר, Nazir, there was this
development of this idea about what type of a thing, not only
are you a נזיר, Nazir, are you not a נזיר, Nazir, but
does it make you a נזיר Nazir for a many, many, many
units, like a thousand units of a נזירות, nezirut, or do we
only interpret it as one נזירות? nezirut? Do we interpret it for
the standard amount of time or for a longer amount of time?
The concept of נזיר עולם, Nazir Olam, which has a special allowance
of getting a trim every month or every year, נזיר שמשון, Nazir
Shimshon, and so on. Those are some of the ideas in the
first פרק. perek.
Now we take a look at the second פרק perek and some
theme that touches on an issue we saw before, so let’s take
a look. הריני נזיר מן הגרוגרות ומן הדבילה. Hareini Nazir min hagerogros
umin hadvela. Somebody says, I’m a נזיר Nazir from, I always get
this mixed up, pressed figs or pressed dates, which is which here?
Figs, and דבילה dvela is dates? One of them is one, right?
The other’s the other?
One is dried figs and one is pressed figs? Okay, fine. Okay,
but anyway,
neither of which are wine or grapes, right? Thank you. Okay, so
that’s all we have to know for us. בית שמאי אומרים, Beis
Shammai omrim, בית שמאי Beis Shammai says נזיר, Nazir, ובית הלל אומרים
אינו נזיר. ubeis hillel omrim eino nazir. He’s a נזיר, Nazir, which
is a זר. zar. We had a discussion before about if somebody
says I’m a נזיר Nazir just from grapes, that then you know
because you did it for a little, you go to the tall
one big unit, the whole thing gets שלעפט schlepped along and you
are a נזיר, Nazir, you can’t just be for one aspect of
it. But how could somebody say that he’s a נזיר Nazir from
גרוגרות grogros and דבילה, dvela, from this thing that isn’t even grapes?
What’s going on with בית שמאי? Beis Shammai? So we’ll take a
look. אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rav Yehuda, says רב יהודה, Rav Yehuda,
עד כאן שאמרו בית שמאי לא אמרו אלא באומר הרי הן עלי
קרבן. ad kahn she'omru Beis Shammai lo amru ela be'omer harei hen
alai korban. Even when בית שמאי Beis Shammai said it, they only
said it if you said they are for me a קרבן, korban,
which is a language of a נדר, neder, they’re forbidden to me.
Now that’s strange, because if you read that in its simple meaning,
it means if you said they’re forbidden to me as a קרבן,
korban, then you become a נזיר. Nazir. Why, what’s the logic there?
So the way רב יהודה Rav Yehuda is really read is,
and maybe although תוספות Tosfos insists באומר, be'omer, but it might work
better if you had כאומר, ke'omer, that what he is saying is
when בית שמאי Beis Shammai says הריני נזיר מן הגרוגרות, Hareini Nazir
min hagerogros, it’s as if you said or interpreted to mean that
you are forbidden on you cannot eat these גרוגרות grogros like a
קרבן, korban, meaning we don’t interpret it as a נזירות. nezirut. We
interpret it as a נדר. neder. So it’s not that you become
a נזיר Nazir because you said you’re not going to eat these
dates. It would be as if you say, I am a נזיר
Nazir from these dates, then
what
would that translate as? You don’t want to eat the dates. Well,
what type of status can you create that you would be forbidden
to eat the dates? That you’re making the dates forbidden to you
as a
נדר. neder.
Okay. So the word נזיר’s Nazir not true?
Right, well, or as תוספות Tosfos points out, להזיר lehazir means to
separate. So we will read the words of הריני נזיר Hareini Nazir
again. I’ll remind some people, somewhat analogous, that at the beginning of
נדרים Nedarim we had a whole discussion about what happens if you
say נדר בלשון שבועה שבועה בלשון נדר, neder belashon shvua שבועה בלשון
נדר shvua belashon neder, which is very common for people, right? Because
they say, a נדר neder that I won’t go into this house.
Okay, so what they really mean is a שבועה, shvua, because a
נדר neder is on objects, a שבועה shvua is on actions, right?
So, you know, a שבועה shvua this food is, you know, אסור
עלי כקרבן assur alai kekorban or something like that. So what they
really mean is a נדר. neder. So a lot of ראשונים Rishonim
say that even if you use the technical word נדר neder or
שבועה, shvua, right, we translate it based on clearly what your intent
was. So if somebody said a נדר neder I won’t go into
this house, what they really mean is a שבועה shvua I won’t
go into this house. Okay, that was a שבועה בלשון נדר. shvua
belashon neder. I’m going to use it, it’s a יד, yad, it’s
a handle towards what you’re actually trying to say. So you could
say the same here by בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, that maybe you
did use the wrong term. Maybe you said נזיר nazir and that
was the wrong term, but bottom line is you’re trying to say
that these dates are forbidden to you, so essentially it’s like a
type of a יד yad for a נדר, neder, and we therefore
we translate it as these dates are forbidden to me as a
קרבן. korban. Okay, or what תוספות Tosfos suggests, the word נזיר nazir
could maybe even mean that. נזיר Nazir means I am removed from
these dates, meaning so that actually is it’s not just the wrong
term, maybe it actually in a particular context has that meaning. But
at least what רב יהודה Rav Yehuda is saying is he’s trying
to give some, you know, way of getting your head around בית
שמאי. Beis Shammai. You said נזיר nazir from dates, what you mean
is the dates are forbidden to me. The problem is that the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma here assumes that בית שמאי Beis Shammai says
you really are a נזיר. nazir. Well, how did that work? How
did you say נזיר nazir from dates and you’re really a נזיר?
nazir? So let’s take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. הריני נזיר
מן הגרוגרות ומן הדבילה, Hareini Nazir min hagerogros umin hadvela, I’m a
נזיר nazir from these dried and pressed dates. בית שמאי אומרים נזיר,
Beis Shammai omrim Nazir, you’re a נזיר. nazir. ואמאי, V'amai, why is
that? מכל אשר יעשה מגפן היין אמר רחמנא. Mikol asher ye'aseh migefen
hayayin amar rachmana. נזירות nezirut only works by wine, and again, we
saw talking before that if you try to be a נזיר nazir
from just one thing of the נזירות, nezirut, like just grapes, okay,
then you’re a נזיר nazir for everything. But here it’s not even
part of the world of נזירות, nezirus, it’s dates, it’s not grapes.
בית
שמאי סברי כרבי מאיר.
Beis
Shammai savrei ke’Rabbi Meir.
So בית שמאי Beis Shammai holds like רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir דאמר
אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה. de’amar ein adam motzi devarav levatalah. A
person does not say his words for naught. Now what is this
position of רבי מאיר? Rabbi Meir? So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says
if somebody says ערך כלי עלי, Erech k’li alai, okay, so basically
in the תורה, Torah, the תורה Torah discusses this idea called ערכין,
Arachin, which are fixed values, okay, and based on if somebody says
the ערך erech of this person is on me to the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, I obligate myself to pay the ערך, erech, so
the תורה Torah says based on the person's age and sex is
determined on how much you pay. It's a fixed value. That is
a very different concept that only works by people, and that goes
by the tables in the תורה. Torah. That is very different from
the concept of דמי, dmei, the value of this person, not the
ערך, erech, I don't know what, you know, I guess I'm looking
for another term for ערך, erech, but anyway דמי dmei is the
market value of this person. So if you say דמי פלוני עלי,
dmei ploni alai, you just, you don't look at any fixed table,
you go ahead and you see what they would go for in
the slave market, right, that's how you'd assign value to human beings.
Or if you say דמי dmei this table עלי, alai, you see
how much it would sell for, okay, דמי dmei this cow עלי,
alai, what would be the going rate. Let's say you said, however,
so דמי dmei works for everything under the sun, ערך erech works
just for human beings and goes by fixed values. Let's say you
say ערך erech this car עלי alai to the בית המקדש. Beis
HaMikdash. Well, there is no ערך erech in the תורה Torah for
cars, there's only an ערך erech for human beings. What do you
do? So רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says you're not חייב chayav anything.
You said a nonsense statement, you're not חייב chayav anything. That's what
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says אין אדם
מוציא דבריו לבטלה, ein adam motzi devarav levatalah, people don't say nonsense
statements, meaningless statements, and therefore what we say is what you mean
is דמי dmei this car עלי, alai, not ערך erech this car
עלי, alai, that's how we'd translate it. Now, whether אין אדם מוציא
דבריו לבטלה ein adam motzi devarav levatalah is a psychological statement that
we're assuming we're going to, you know, oh, well, you must have
meant this because people don't סתם stam talk nonsense, or I assume
it's more of a legal statement which is, right, I assume it,
yeah.
It's obviously people will never say stupid, yeah, people
don't make stupid jokes either, right. But anyway, or whether it's a
legal statement which is basically saying somebody said something with, you know,
not in like conversation, somebody said something clearly in some type of
a, you know, legal context, obviously with meant to impart on it
some type of legal meaning, we're going to, we're going to define
a, a, you know, an interpretation for that, a meaningful interpretation for
that. You know, okay, we don't know what he was thinking, but
for that type of a statement we will give it a, we,
you know, we will not call it a meaningless statement, we will
give it some type of a meaningful interpretation. So that is רבי
מאיר. Rabbi Meir. So the גמרא Gemara says well that works with
בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. Yes, you said something meaningless, הריני נזיר מן
הגרוגרות, Hareini nazir min hagrogros, it's saying like ערך כלי עלי. Erech
k’li alai. Okay, so we can either say what you said was
a meaningless statement and you said nothing, or we could say that
what you really meant was to say something meaningful, you know, we're
going to interpret it in a legally meaningful in a halachically meaningful
way. Now, here's the only problem. Problem is that when you say
ערך כלי עלי, Erech k’li alai, we can interpret it meaningfully by
saying the word ערך erech was really meant דמי, dmei, and therefore
the whole sentence makes sense. Once the ערך erech term was a
little inaccurate, just change that term a little bit to דמי dmei
and it all makes sense. But הריני נזיר מן הגרוגרות, Hareini nazir
min hagrogros, the whole statement well won't make sense except according to
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. If the word נזיר nazir means forbidden to
me מן הגרוגרות, min hagrogros, or something like that, that works like
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. But to actually say I am a נזיר
nazir means the גרוגרות grogros part is going to just be discarded.
So it is a jump from the idea of רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. It's not just a reinterpreting of a term, it's actually saying
because you said הריני נזיר, Hareini nazir, we're going to say that's
a binding statement, אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה, ein adam motzi devarav
levatalah, and we'll just ignore the end part of it. Yes.
Why can't there be a middle position? Why can't when he says
נזיר, nazir, that's meaningful, נזיר, nazir, and I'm going to add to
my נזירות nezirus an abstinence from this other food?
So
the גמרא Gemara is going to get to that in a minute,
and that's going to help us with understanding the מן הגרוגרות, min
hagrogros, that we're going to really say not just like אין אדם
מוציא דבריו לבטלה ein adam motzi devarav levatalah look at the whole
statement, but we're going to say the first part you said you're
a נזיר, nazir, and the second part doesn't undermine it, so the
second part is just nonsense so we ignore the second part.
No, no, but I
didn't ignore it, I plus like two things. Exactly. Okay, but that's
not an option given in the משנה. Mishnah. In the משנה Mishnah
you have רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda that says you're just אסור מן
הגרוגרות assur min hagrogros according to בית שמאי, Beis Shammai, and the
תנא קמא Tanna Kamma that says that you're a נזיר. nazir. Nobody
says you're both.
Yeah, the question is why not?
I don't know. Okay, I guess you could, in theory you could
have had that. Okay, so let's take, let's continue. So that's רבי
מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that's בית שמאי Beis Shammai כרבי מאיר, ke’Rabbi Meir,
אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה, ein adam motzi devarav levatalah, except again
as was said stated here, it's not exactly רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
because we are still ignoring the end of your sentence. ובית הלל
סברי, U’Beis Hillel savri, בית הלל Beis Hillel holds, כרבי יוסי, ke’Rabbi
Yossi, like רבי יוסי, Rabbi Yossi, דאמר בגמר דבריו אדם נתפס, de’amar
begmar devarav adam nitpas,
that a person goes by the end of their words, והאי נדר
ופתחו עמו הוא, vehai neder upitcho imo hu,
and this is a נדר neder with the opening at the end,
okay, with sort of like it undermines itself. Now, it is interesting
that the גמרא Gemara could have more easily just said that בית
הלל Beis Hillel *Beis Hillel* holds that מאמצעי דבריו לא תליא *ma'atze'i
devarov lo talya*, you do say nonsense statements, but what the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* wants to say is even within, and this is essentially
what we just got through saying, even within רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
*Rebbi Meir* that we want to say that you never say something
that you don't say a nonsense statement, but here you got the
second part of it. Fine, you don't say a nonsense statement, but
you still said נזיר nazir. *nazir* and you said מן הגרוגרות min
hagrogros. *mina grogros*. So the מן הגרוגרות min hagrogrot. *mina grogros* reflects
the idea that you know you were trying to be a נזיר
nazir *nazir*, but ultimately you you know you changed your mind or
ultimately you didn't really know what you were saying. So, right, it's
one thing to say, we'll say אין אדם... we'll all agree like
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, *Rebbi Meir*, אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה ein
adam motzi devarav l'vatalah, *ein adam motzi devarov l'vatala*. If you say
ערך כלי עלי erech kli alai *erech klee alai*, you'll say it
means דמי כלי עלי damei kli alai, *d'mei klee alai*. Okay, but
here the problem is is that we can't just reinterpret the sentence.
There's still this nonsense end part of it, okay? And that's what
בית הלל Beit Hillel *Beis Hillel* holds. Now what is this רבי
יוסי Rabbi Yose, *Rebbi Yossi*?
Therefore the doubt the nonsense part of it undermines the whole part.
Undermines the whole part. We yes, we will say the whole statement
is meaningful. It's a whole statement that's meaningful that the second part
of it undermines the first part of it, okay? It's not just
translating it so it's not nonsense. There's actually two contradictory parts to
it. Okay, so the case is that a person says הרי זה
תמורת עולה תמורת שלמים tmuras olah tmuras shelamim, *harei zeh tmuras olah
tmuras shelamim*. Right? This animal is an exchange for an עולה *olah*
and an exchange for a שלמים *shelamim*. So some opinions are well
the תמורת עולה tmuras olah, *tmuras olah* part works, it can't be
both, so you just ignore the second part. רבי יוסי Rebbi Yosi
*Rebbi Yossi* says no, you do look at the whole thing and
even though there's a logical contradiction, what is it, an exchange of
an עולה *olah* or an exchange of a שלמים *shelamim*, it has
both קדושות *kedushas* and you can't bring it as a קרבן *korban*,
okay, but you can redeem it and use half the money for
an עולה *olah* and half the money for a שלמים *shelamim*. So
that's a case where the second part really contradicts the first part
and we just have to somehow say both are true and deal
with that bizarre reality. So here too both are going to be
true. It's not לבטלה *l'vatala*, we can even work within רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir *Rebbi Meir*. Fine, you got a statement that you're a
נזיר nazir *nazir* and you got a statement that you think נזירות
nezirus *nezirus* is about not eating dates. So the bottom line is
that it's not a real קבלת נזירות nezirus *kabalas nezirus*. Okay. Now
let's just I just want to read the one line here in
the תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos*, I was about to say the ר"ן *Ran*
again. So it says,
where is it, so
תוספות Tosafot *Tosfos* says it's about one, two, three, four, five, six,
six lines down in the wide lines, he says like this, one
starts with the word לשלמים *lishlamim*, maybe it's five lines down, הכי
נמי דגמר דבריו שאמר גרוגרות grogros. נתפס וכיון שאין נזירות nezirus, בגרוגרות
לא הוי נזיר nazir. ואף על גב דבתחילה אמר הריני נזיר hareini
nazir חזר בתוך כדי דיבור דאמר d'amar מן הגרוגרות min hagrogrot. ובגמר
דבריו אדם נתפס כאילו נדר neder, בתוך כדי דיבור מצא פתח pesach
לו וחרטה דכיון שנדרו ופתחו עמו לא חל כלל *hachi nami digmar
devarov she'amar grogros nitpas v'keivan she'ein nezirus bigrogros lo havei nazir v'af
al gav d'vitchila amar harei'ni nazir chazar betoch k'dei dibbur d'amar mina
grogros uvigmar devarov adam nitpas ke'ilu neder betoch k'dei dibbur matza pesach
lo v'charata d'keivan shenidro upitcho imo lo chal klal*. Okay? So he
basically says that if you said נזיר nazir *nazir* and then you
said oh but I only meant מן הגרוגרות min hagrogrot, *mina grogros*,
so you're like either you're being חוזר chozer, בתוך כדי דיבור *chozer
toch k'dei dibbur* or clear at some level you clearly didn't know
what you were talking about. So therefore yes אין אדם מוציא דבריו
לבטלה ein adam motzi devarav l'vatalah, *ein adam motzi devarov l'vatala* but
it's a contradictory statement and the second half contradicts the first half.
There was a question? No? Okay. So, alright, so that's what the
גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is
saying here.
One minute.
Oh so by the way Rabbi Dov I should read the next
line because תוספות Tosafot, *Tosfos* asks your question. He says, ואם תאמר
*ve'im tomar*, let me read another line in תוספות Tosafos *Tosfos*, והא
דאמר רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi, דבגמר דבריו אדם נתפס פירוש אף דבגמר
דבריו אדם נתפס שווי תמורת עולה ותמורת שלמים *vehama Rebbi Yossi digmar
devarov adam nitpas peirush af digmar devarov adam nitpas shavei tmuras olah
v'tmuras shelamim* in רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi *Rebbi Yossi*'s case we don't
say they're contradictory, we say it's both an עולה *olah* and a
שלמים *shelamim*. So here too let's say both. הכי נמי נתפוס לשון
ראשון נמי דקאמר נזיר nazir. ואי נזיר nazir, מן היין ונזיר מן
הגרוגרות min hagrogarot ונדור מן הגרוגרות min hagrogarot *hachi nami nitpos lashon
rishon nami d'ka'amar nazir v'ai nazir min hayayin v'nazir mina grogrot v'nadur
mina grogrot*. And here's exactly your question: why not say both? So
we say that the statement includes both parts, so say both are
true A and B. So he says, יש לומר דהכא מפורש בתמורה
היכא דדבריו סותרים זה את At, זה לא יכול לומר דסיפא לפירושי
תחילה דבריו קאתי הלכך חייב בשני לשונות *yesh lomar d'hacha meforesh bitmura
heicha d'devarav sotrim zeh et zeh lo yakhol lomar desafei l'pirushei techilas
devarov ka'asi hilchach chayiv b'shnei lashonot*. So interesting if they really are
not at all compatible, an עולה *olah* and a שלמים *shelamim*, we
say we mean A and B והוי תמורת עולה ותמורת שלמים *v'hava
tmuras olah v'tmuras shelamim*. אבל במתניתין איכא לומר דסיפא לפירושי רישא *aval
b'matnisin ika lomar desafei l'pirushei reisha*. When you say גרוגרות grogros, *grogros*
you're explaining that's my idea of נזירות nezirus *nezirus*, נזירות nezirus *nezirus*
makes me forbidden in גרוגרות grogros *grogros*. האי דקאמר נזיר nazir. לאו
מן היין קאמר דאי האי נזיר nazir *hai d'ka'amar nazir lav minayayin
ka'amar d'ihai nazir* from wine אלא Ella, גרוגרות grogarot. הלכך גמר דבריו
עיקר הם לתפוס ולא בתחילה דבריו *ela grogros hilchach gmar devarav ikar
hem litpos v'lo techilas devarov*. Okay so basically it does say yeah
there are some times we say you mean A and B but
that's when A and B maybe are seen as not one explaining
the other, תמורת עולה *tmuras olah* doesn't explain תמורת שלמים tmuras shelamim
*tmuras shelamim* or vice versa, they're two separate things, they're equal weight,
we say you mean both. Okay, but when you say
נזיר nazir מן *nazir min*... So
what?
Just to say really, you know, that the בית שמאי Beis Shammai
say it should work.
No, you think that no, it's not going to be מן הגרוגרות.
Yes, it's גמר דברו, gmar devaro, but גמר דברו gmar devaro is
to explain that that's your concept of נזירות nezirus which isn't a
נזירות nezirus and therefore you're not a נזיר.
Nazir, But isn't he saying the motive, in other words, that's a
hermeneutic? I have a statement with two halves.
I can read it as two independent parts that don't contradict each
other, or I can say the last statement interprets the first and
therefore undermines it. He doesn't say legally why we are motivated to
apply one reading as opposed to the other.
Well, because תמורת שלמים cannot interpret תמורת עולה, but נזיר מן הגרוגרות,
nazir min hagrogros, that's just the פשט. pshat. This guy thinks you
can be a נזיר Nazir, from גרוגרות. grogrot. That's the simple meaning,
it's what he's saying. He's saying he's a נזיר nazir, from גרוגרות,
grogrot, right? If you say תמורת עולה תמורת שלמים, which one? Make
up your mind, you said two things. But נזיר מן הגרוגרות nazir
min hagrogros means you think you can be a נזיר מן הגרוגרות
nazir min hagrogros and you can't, right? So that's why, so basically
over here we have נזיר מן הגרוגרות, nazir min hagrogros, right? So
basically what do we have? We have first the idea of רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir that says you could just say that's a nonsense
statement and המותי דברו לבטלה. amoti devaro levatala. But you have בית
שמאי Beis Shammai going like רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, אין המותי דברו
לבטלה, ain amoti devaro levatala, but ironically that means we'll take the
part that works and we'll reject the rest of it and you're
a נזיר. nazir And then the גמרא Gemara says according to רבי
יוסי, Rabbi Yosi right, that says that בגמר דברו הוא נתפס b'gmar
devaro ad nitpas is we'll take the whole statement and we'll use
the גרוגרות grogrot, to explain what the word נזיר nazir. means and
then that's nonsense and then it's a weird type of נזירות, nezirut
a נזירות neziros. you made up, and therefore the whole thing gets
sort of like rejected. And we're not going to explain this as
two things because it really can be like one big thing. Now
how that is effectively different than the idea of המותי דברו לבטלה,
amoti devaro levatala, I really don't get it, right? Because it's basically
saying that's a nonsense statement like ערך כלי עלי erech kli alai
and therefore okay, you said a nonsense statement. So here you're saying
the same thing, you said a sentence, you wanted it to work,
but it winds up when we take the whole thing that it's
a nonsense statement. Okay, but that's what בית הלל Beit Hillel says,
that you go by the end, the end explains the beginning and
therefore you are a, the whole thing is your weird idea of
נזירות nezirut, which is not a נזיר.
nazir Isn't it the same as המותי דברו לבטלה amoti devaro levatala
and סיפא לשון ראשון s'fa lashon rishon according to רבי מאיר halakhically?
Yes, so that's what I said, it's not clear how it's making
a difference there. I'm sure there could be differences. Okay, so גמרא
Gemara says like this, okay, ואימא דפתחו עמו. v'aima de-pis'cho imo. ובית
שמאי נמי נדר ופתחו עמו הוא. U'Beis Shammai nami neder u-pis'cho imo
hu. And now the גמרא's Gemara giving it up because the גמרא
Gemara... basically says look, I get אין המותי דברו לבטלה, ain amoti
devaro levatala, but we still have this problem. If you say ערך
erech כלי עלי and we say ערך erech, it can't mean ערך,
you have to mean דמי כלי עלי, we'll reinterpret that word שלום
על ישראל. shalom al Yisrael. But here you can't say אין המותי
דברו לבטלה ain amoti devaro levatala and ignore the second part of
the statement. You gotta do something with the second part of the
statement. So doesn't בית שמאי Beis Shammai agree that even if you
take the whole thing, this thing has to somehow explain that part
and you still become up with something that's meaningless? Okay, so we're
back to the point of we don't want to ignore the statement
but what are you going to do if you can't accept the
whole thing? What allows you to just ignore the end? So where
are you with that? אלא, בית שמאי סברא ליה Beis Shammai savra
lei כרבי מאיר k'Rabbi Meir דאמר אין המותי דברו
לבטלה. ain amoti devaro levatala. That sounds familiar, the language here sometimes
gets a little repetitive. וכיון דאמר הריני נזיר V'keivan d'amar hareni nazir
הוי ליה נזיר. havei lei nazir. Okay, as soon as you say
נזיר, nazir, that's you become a
נזיר. nazir כי קאמר מן הגרוגרות ומן הדבילה, Ki q'amar min hagrogros
u'min hadeveila, when you add the second part, לשלולי הוא דקאתי. l'shalulei
hu de-ka-ati. Then you're coming to basically,
that's not seen as interpreting the first part of your statement, that's
seen as a second statement and that's coming to undermine the first
and basically say oh actually I regret it, it's some type of
a way of, some excuse. We don't view it as one statement,
we view it as a second statement that's coming to find a
פתח and a way of getting out of the first. ובית שמאי
לטעמייהו דאמרי U'Beis Shammai l'tama'aihu d'amri and בית שמאי Beit Shammai goes
according to their reasoning who says אין שאלה בהקדש ein sheila b'hekdesh
that once you sanctify something, although you can make a שאלה sheila
for a נדר, neder, you make something forbidden to you of a
vow, you can go ahead and go to a חכם chacham and
get it undone. If you make something sanctified to the בית המקדש
Beis Hamikdash you cannot. Now logically you would have said נזירות nezirut.
is a type of a נדר, but וכיון דאין שאלה בהקדש אין
שאלה בנזירות. v'keivan d'ein sheila b'hekdesh ein sheila b'nezirus. נזירות nezirut. is
like הקדש, hekdesh, you cannot undo it. Why? So תוספות Tosafot explains
because it says קדוש יהיה גדל פרע שער ראשו kadosh yihyeh gadel
pera sear rosho because it calls the hair holy and there is
a sense, let's face it, not just calls the hair, there is
this sense that the נזיר nazir is somehow like a type of
a כהן, kohen, right? I mean on the one hand כהן גדול
kohen gadol cuts hair, נזיר nazir. doesn't, but he's not טמא למתים,
tamei l'mesim, he's trying to make... whole self like has this elevated
status. There is some more this sense of קדושה kedusha that gets
associated with a נזיר, Nazir so that is like the idea of
הקדש hekdesh and it cannot be undone. So now we understand the
difference. רבי יוסי says look at the whole sentence. You said נזיר
מן הגרוגרות, Nazir min hagrogrot, so your concept of נזירות nezirus. is
מן הגרוגרות. That is foolish, that is nothing, so you said nothing.
בית שמאי Beit Shammai says I am not going to be able
to, I am not prepared to explain it that way. You know
why? Because that would have the effect of being מוציא דבריו לבטלה.
motzi devarav levatala. And I do not want to end up with
מוציא דבריו לבטלה. motzi devarav levatala. So normally, so what am I
going to do to make it not מוציא דבריו לבטלה? motzi devarav
levatala? Well, I will say you said two sentences. This does not
explain this, it is not one big sentence. First you said נזיר,
nazir, that was meaningful. Then you said, oh wait, wait, I just
wanted to be מן הגרוגרות. I will interpret that as a second
sentence. So that at least it will not be the whole thing
is nonsense because this part is meaningful. Now, why is it when
you do say מן הגרוגרות, cannot that come along and actually say,
okay, look, at least you have חרטה charata you want to undo
it, you want to limit it or something? בית שמאי Beit Shammai
says no, once it took effect it is too late to do
anything. Okay?
So in theory, בית הלל's Beit Hillel debate with בית שמאי Beit
Shammai could be, I agree it is two parts, but I think
you can be מתיר נדר. matir neder. Okay? You could have said
it that way, but then you maybe would have to go to
a חכם chacham to מתיר matir it, which is why בית הלל
Beit Hillel goes even further and says פתחו עמו. pitcho imo. I
do not view it as two parts. I look at the whole
thing. בגמר דבריו אדם נתפס. bigmar devarav adam nitpas. I do not
stop and look at the first part of your sentence. I let
you finish your thought. Okay? By the time you are done with
your sentence you meant something nonsense. Okay? That is what בית הלל
Beit Hillel says, whereas בית שמאי Beit Shammai says no, this is
meaningful, that is a second part, and that second part once this
was in place, that cannot come to undo it. Yes, Dov?
But does not, that does not take into account תוספות's Tosafot. view,
right? Which is this is like a, it is like the תוך
כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur kind of thing.
Yeah, so what he does is, so תוך כדי דיבור כחזרה.
toch kedei
dibbur kachazara.
That is what I was thinking, right. So that is, yeah, so
it is a good question like whether בית שמאי Beit Shammai, would
even not hold of תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur according to
this. Yeah.
Meaning if I said it, am I really not allowed to,
even תוך כדי, toch kedei, to go back?
I mean, just, no, I guess not?
I mean, if you take a look at תוספות, Tosafot he says
ולכאורה קשיא v'lechora kashya for like the new תוספות Tosafot four lines
down in the wide lines, לאו דוקא לכולי דהא לא בא לשאלה.
lav davka lichulei deha lo ba lishaila. He
is not coming to ask a חכם, chacham, he is שואל, shoel,
אלא מתחרט, ela mitcharet,
but he immediately regrets it. וחוזר בו קודם שבא לשאול לחכם על
נדרו מחמת חרטה. vechozer bo kodem sheba lishol lechacham al nidro machmat
charata. It
is because of basic חרטה charata like immediately after I said it
I regretted it. שחכם מוציא לו פתח לחרטה והוי נדר טעות ובטל.
shechacham motzi lo petach lacharata vehavi neder taut ubatel. So he basically
says you are חוזר בו chozer bo immediately, it should be annulled,
right? So and nevertheless we basically say that it does not work.
אין שאלה להקדש ein she'eila lehekdesh etc. So it is funny, you're
right. I mean it's תוך כדי דיבור toch kedei dibbur and all
those types of things, but somehow this idea of אין שאלה להקדש
ein she'eila lehekdesh also means like there is no חזרה להקדש. chazara
lehekdesh. It is sort of like the סוגיא sugya we had in
the end of נדרים Nedarim if you might remember, that תוך כדי
דיבור toch kedei dibbur does not work on all things. So it
seems like that's pretty much the statement the גמרא's Gemara making. Yes.
See, the only way I can make that make sense in my
mind is if you really want to be חוזר, chozer just say
'I didn't' as opposed to trying to reinterpret. And once you start
trying to reinterpret then
that is where it becomes a little dicey, right? Because if he
really would have gone all out and be חוזר chozer, it would
have worked, right? As opposed to saying 'oh, I'm reinterpreting it', which
like, no, you cannot kind of reinterpret because then you have already
said the first part. If you're going to be חוזר, chozer. be
חוזר. If you're going to be reinterpret, you're reinterpreting it in sort
of like a wrong
way, but he did make two halves of the statement then. You
know what I mean?
No. What are you saying?
The גמרא... Gemara maybe if he would have actually really reinterpreted everyone
would have... I mean חזרה chazara on it.
Why? But the גמרא Gemara does not do it because the גמרא
Gemara
in נדרים Nedarim
says that חזרה chazara does not work. Is there anything? No, the
גמרא Gemara in נדרים Nedarim says there are things that חזרה chazara
does not work. But it did not say שאלה... she'eila... according to...
did not say הקדש hekdesh according to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai but
in theory that could be true. It sounds a little bit from
תוספות Tosafot, that is the case.
But anyway. All right, so let's take a look.
One minute. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. One minute, let
me just check one thing in תוספות. Tosafot Yeah, so basically
yeah, that is what תוספות Tosafot says. That the גמרא's Gemara basic
position in בית שמאי Beit Shammai. is that once it took effect,
if the whole thing we interpreted at the outset as one big
unit, it would have meant nothing and it would not have taken
effect. But once it took effect, it cannot be reversed. But I
think the point that Dov makes is the correct one, that it
sounds like we are saying that even though even תוך כדי דיבור
toch kedei dibbur does not work according to תוספות according to בית
שמאי. Beit Shammai. Once part of it takes effect, you're stuck. If
we were to look at the whole thing as one unit, it
never would have taken effect. But once it takes effect, there is
no reversing of it, not even without going to a חכם, chacham,
but even based on חזרה chazara and חרטה charata and תוך כדי
דיבור. toch kedei dibbur. none of that seems to work according to
בית שמאי. Beit Shammai Okay, and now the גמרא Gemara says like
this: ובית הלל סברי לה כרבי שמעון. u'Beit Hillel savrei leh k'Rabbi
Shimon.
Now בית הלל Beit Hillel, holds like רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon again
why you have to go to רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon is again
not clear, before a minute ago we were talking about רבי יוסי,
it's like throwing in everybody who ever discussed how hermeneutics of how
to interpret your speech. Okay, so until now we were just saying
that בית הלל Beit Hillel holds you look at the whole sentence,
in the end it winds up being a the end explains the
beginning and never took effect, it was never meaningful. But that's a
sort of like an אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה adam motzi devarav l'vatalah
at the end of the day, we're saying that in the end
the statement will have no meaning. So now we're going to show
another position like that of רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. דתנן d'tnan we
taught in the משנה, Mishnah, רבי שמעון פוטר שלא התנדב כדרך המתנדבים.
Rabbi Shimon potair shelo hitnadev k'derech hamitnadvim. If somebody says, "I will
bring a מנחה mincha out of barley," okay, so there's no מנחה
mincha you can be free will offer out of barley, there's only
מנחה mincha out of barley is a מנחת סוטה minchat sotah or
a מנחת חוטא, minchat chotei, so there's no סוטה, sotah, what did
I
say סוטה, sotah, סוטה, sotah, anyway, there's no such thing as a
מנחה mincha out of barley. So when you say "I'm going to
bring a מנחה mincha out of barley," what do we do? That's
exactly a very nice parallel to הריני נזיר מן הגרוגרות. hareini nazir
min hagrogarot. You have the concept but you have the sort of
contents of it like wrong. Okay, so the specifics wrong. So רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon says one opinion is that, okay, you have to
bring a normal מנחה, mincha, you said מנחה, mincha, you got the
specifics wrong, we ignore the specifics, we said you wanted to bring
a מנחה, mincha, you'll bring a
מנחה. mincha. ורבי שמעון v'Rabbi Shimon says no, שלא התנדב כדרך המתנדבים.
shelo hitnadev k'derech hamitnadvim. You took a vow which was not a
normal vow, if in the end we have to say you said
nonsense, so you said nonsense, but you took accepted a מנחה mincha
of barley and there's no such thing as a מנחה mincha of
barley. So that actually seems like a very nice parallel debate, right?
You got it? You said "I'm going to be x" and then
you filled in the specifics in a way that doesn't work within
what the x is. There's no such thing as a מנחה mincha
of barley, no such thing as a נזיר מן הגרוגרות. nazir min
hagrogarot. Okay, so bottom line what have we said? We've said that
for בית הלל, Beit Hillel you look at the whole sentence and
you've got this nonsense sentence of נזיר מן הגרוגרות. nazir min hagrogarot.
So we basically say that we don't split it in half, we
look at the whole thing, you said nonsense, either that's an idea
of אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה adam motzi devarav l'vatalah or בסוף דבריו
אדם נתפס b'sof devarav adam nitpas so the end result is that
it's meaningless, or another way of saying that is לא התנדב כדרך
המתנדבים, lo hitnadev k'derech hamitnadvim, you didn't do it in the right
way. One way or another way, it's a way of saying we
are prepared to accept the idea that you said this whole thing
which doesn't make sense and the effect is nothing takes effect. Okay,
whereas בית שמאי Beit Shammai. says we look at the first part,
we ignore the second part. The whole thing doesn't work, we're going
to focus on the first part, אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה, ein
adam motzi devarav l'vatala, you became a נזיר, nazir the second part
we ignore, we say that wasn't intended or it was a חזרה
chazarah and the חזרה chazarah is not meaningful. Okay, and in the
course of this the גמרא Gemara. threw in five different positions of
תנאים. Tannaim. Okay, מתניתין דלא כי האי תנא. matnitin d'lo k'hai tana.
Our משנה Mishnah top of טו עמוד ב tet-vav amud bet is
not like the following תנא. tana. דתניא d'tanya we taught in a
ברייתא, braita,
רבי נתן אומר, Rabbi Natan omer, בית שמאי אומרים Beit Shammai omrim
נדור ונזיר. nadur v'nazir. Here you go, Dovi, here's some of the
variations you were looking for. Here the difference, a third approach on
the debate of בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי. Beit Shammai
According to רבי נתן, Rabbi Natan, בית שמאי Beit Shammai says you're
both a נזיר nazir and forbidden from the dates. Okay, so הריני
נזיר nazir. period, מן הגרוגרות and you're also forbidden from גרוגרות. gerogerot,
נדור מן הגרוגרות nadur min hagrogarot and a נזיר. nazir That's the
way we salvage the whole statement is we say it means A
and B. ובית הלל אומרים u'Beit Hillel omrim נדור ואין נזיר. nadur
v'ein nazir. And בית הלל Beit Hillel says what רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda thought that בית שמאי Beit Shammai would say, and נזיר מן
הגרוגרות nazir min hagrogarot we'll have to salvage something out of that
whole statement, so we say נזיר מן הגרוגרות nazir min hagrogarot means
נדור מן הגרוגרות. nadur min hagrogarot. Okay, so that's a nice way
of explaining the debate, everybody salvages the statement in one way or
another.
בית שמאי סברי לה כרבי מאיר וכרבי יהודה. Beit Shammai savrei lah
k'Rabbi Meir u'k'Rabbi Yehuda. בית שמאי Beit Shammai, holds like רבי מאיר
that says אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה, ein adam motzi devarav l'vatala
so therefore you got the whole statement, so נזיר nazir, means נזיר,
nazir and he holds like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda who says, now
which one is the רבי יהודה? Rabbi Yehuda?
The גמרא Gemara. בסוף דבריו... b'sof devarav...
no that was רבי יוסי said בסוף דבריו אדם נתפס. b'sof devarav
adam nitpas.
The רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda is, oh, רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's read
of בית שמאי, Beit Shammai which is נזיר מן הגרוגרות nazir min
hagrogarot means נדור מן הגרוגרות. nadur min hagrogarot. Okay, so basically בית
שמאי Beit Shammai. wants to according to this like רבי מאיר, you
don't want to throw out any part of the sentence, so נזיר
nazir means נזיר nazir and מן הגרוגרות means נדור מן הגרוגרות nadur
min hagrogarot like רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda read בית שמאי. Beit Shammai
Okay, so בית שמאי Beit Shammai wants to have you have the
whole sentence.
Okay, ובית הלל סברי לה כרבי יוסי u'Beit Hillel savrei leh k'Rabbi
Yosi and בית הלל Beit Hillel holds like רבי יוסי that says
בגמר דבריו אדם נתפס, b'gmar devarav adam nitpas, which means you look
at somehow the entire sentence and you give it one meaning, and
the one meaning we give the entire sentence if we want to
maintain all parts of it is נזיר מן הגרוגרות nazir min hagrogarot
means נדור מן הגרוגרות. nadur min hagrogarot. Okay, so that's a different
variation which has everybody giving this sentence more weight, בית שמאי Beit
Shammai sees both two halves and each half is both. binding separately,
and בית הלל Beit Hillel. gives the whole thing a meaning, which
is forbidden from גרוגרות. gerogerot, Okay, that's one version of this. לישנא
אחרינא, Lishna achrina, another version. נדור... Nadur...
אמרי ליה רבי נתן. Amrei lei Rabbi Natan. רבי נתן Rabbi Natan
said... אמרי ליה. Amrei lei. They said to him, I'm sorry. לישנא
אחרינא אמרי ליה. Lishna achrina amrei lei. A different language version of
this was said. רבי נתן אומר בית שמאי אומרים נדור ואינו נזיר.
Rabbi Natan omer Beit Shammai omrim Nadur ve'eino Nazir. Now that is
רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. So this is a version that בית שמאי
Beit Shammai. said you're a נדור, nadur, you're forbidden from the גרוגרות,
gerogerot, but you're not a נזיר. nazir, That's רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's
version of בית שמאי. Beit Shammai Okay, ובית הלל אומרים לא נדור
ולא נזיר. u'Beit Hillel omrim lo nadur velo nazir. You're neither, which
is just our משנה. Mishnah. You're nothing. So that's an easy version.
בית שמאי Beit Shammai. כרבי יהודה, k'Rabbi Yehuda, that's רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi
Yehuda's version of בית שמאי. Beit Shammai, You take the whole sentence,
you give it one meaning, and the one meaning is the word
נזיר nazir means נדור nadur in this case and it means you're
forbidden from the dates. ובית הלל כרבי שמעון, u'Beit Hillel k'Rabbi Shimon,
and בית הלל Beit Hillel, goes like רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Which
is the רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon about... now I'm getting confused. Which
is רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon here? Oh, לא נתנדב כדרך המתנדבים. lo
nitnadev k'derech hamitnadvim. That we're prepared that your whole sentence means nothing.
Okay, fine. So different variations but we got all the possibilities. Basically,
do you... are you prepared to say the whole sentence means nothing?
The best analogy... the best statement about that is רבי שמעון... Rabbi
Shimon... either אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה adam motzi devarav l'vatala or רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon who says לא נתנדב כדרך המתנדבים, lo nitnadev k'derech
hamitnadvim, which means you could say something, you got the details wrong,
we throw the whole sentence out. That's בית הלל. Beit Hillel. Or
if you want to have the sentence mean something, and you're not
prepared for it to not mean anything halakhically, and that's אין אדם
מוציא דבריו לבטלה, and then you have three options. Your three options
are you're only a נזיר, nazir we throw out the second part,
we say that's like a חזרה hazara and חזרה hazara doesn't help
by נזירות. nezirus That's option number one. Option number two is you're
only אסור assur from the גרוגרות, grogros. נזיר nazir means נדור. nadur.
And the third option is you have two statements here, you're a
נזיר nazir and you're נדור מן הגרוגרות. nadur min hagrogrot. But that
starts from an orientation that we basically are not prepared to throw
out the sentence so we're going to find you... as one of
those three meanings is a... is the meaning we're going to give
you here.
Yeah, I was just thinking about... אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה is
a really powerful idea. It really essentially means anytime a human being
says something, they had some thought in mind. I might not be
able to figure out what it is, but on some level they
mean something. We might not be able to interpret it with legal
force. But it's a powerful statement about...
Yeah, I do wonder, I mean I appreciate that, I do wonder
whether it's limited to cases where we're dealing with things that are
legal speech acts, you know, and right if like we're just having
I don't know a conversation. I mean you can imagine another case
where it's halakhically relevant. We're just having a conversation, I don't know
I'm about to sell you a car and I mention something in
passing or whatever. And they would say wait wait, was that relevant
to the sale? Do we give that... do we say that I
was actually making some stipulation or this or that? So maybe we
could say that like anything I'm saying we assume has some meaning
in this context. But somehow I think it's a little bit different
when we're talking about something which clearly is a speech act. Right.
Exactly, yeah.
Because I think that the way you've been using the word meaningful,
it's as legally meaningful. A lot of these sentences, for instance the
barley, actually is different than the examples before in the sense that
I could see how somebody could make that mistake.
Ah, so you've anticipated the next line of the גמרא.
gemara It's logically meaningful. Right, Wittgenstein is going to hold that this
is a syntactically meaningful sentence. Right.
But it doesn't halakhically make any sense.
Right, right. And thank you, and that idea that it is an...
is it a mistake we could have expected? Exactly. Like the other
one would be נזיר מן הגרוגרות, Nazir min hagrogrot, which presumably nobody
gets confused. Exactly, perfect transition to the next גמרא. gemara So let's
take a look.
Okay, so תנן התם, tnan hatam,
we taught over there. האומר, ha'omer, now we get to this discussion
about the מנחה Mincha which is the most comparable discussion. האומר הרי
עלי מנחה להביא מן השעורים, ha'omer harei alai mincha lehavi min hase'orim,
I accept upon myself a מנחה Mincha to bring from barley. יביא
מן החטים, yavi min hachittim, go ahead and bring it from the
wheat. קמח, kemach, I'll bring a מנחה Mincha out of like קמח,
kemach, like bran, יביא סולת, yavi solet, you have to bring it
from fine flour because there is no מנחה Mincha from קמח. kemach.
שלא בשמן
ולבונה, shelo b'shemen ulevona, I'm gonna bring a מנחה Mincha without the
oil and the frankincense, יביאנה בשמן ולבונה, yavi'enah b'shemen ulevona,
bring it with the oil. We basically say you meant a מנחה,
Mincha, these other qualifications don't work with a מנחה, Mincha, so we
just ignore the end of your sentence. חצי
עשרון, chatzi issaron, I'm gonna bring a half of an עשרון, issaron,
which doesn't exist as a מנחה, Mincha, יביא עשרון שלם, yavi issaron
shalem, you have to bring the minimum amount which is a full
עשרון. עשרון isaron isaron. וחצי,
one and a half עשרונות, issaronot, and again you can only do
it in עשרון issaron. units a מנחה, Mincha, יביא שנים, yavi shnayim,
bring two, because which is interesting because that's like saying an עשרון
issaron and a half, and a half doesn't mean, so we'll give
some meaning to that, because there we could have said if you
say one and a half we'll just say one, right I guess
it could have been possible there but we'll interpret it more... you
know, to something that will include the חצי עשרון. chatzi isaron. Okay.
רבי שמעון פוטר. Rabbi Shimon poter. רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon says in
all these cases you're exempt. שלא התנדב כדרך המתנדבים. shelo hitnadev k'derech
hamitnadbim. You did not do it in a normal way. Interesting, again,
I think the most interesting one is the one of one and
a half. If you say I'm going to make a מנחה mincha
of one and a half, he says don't bring anything because no
such thing exists as a מנחה mincha of one and a half,
even though the one does. Everything else was limiting, I'm going to
do less. Here you're going to say you're going to do more,
but not in a way that's a legitimate מנחה. mincha.
But the פסוק pasuk does say עשרון issaron עשרון. Maybe that's an
echoing in the background.
Right, well clearly it's based on that it needs to be those
units, but you could have said for him drop the half and
bring the main, but no, as a whole thing, it doesn't exist,
don't bring anything. Now, מאן תנא דכי אמר הרי עלי מנחה מן
השעורים יביא מן החיטים? man tanna deki amar harei alai mincha min
hase'orim yavi min hachittim? So now, this next סוגיא sugya is like
I think much simpler than the early one because this directly starts
with a concrete debate in a very parallel סוגיא sugya of our
משנה, mishnah, you know, and it's totally going to focus on this
case as opposed to the other one we quoted like ten different
תנאים tannaim that with, you know, it threw them all together. So
this is going to focus very much on this, on this particular
parallel between this discussion and our משנה. mishnah. So who is the
תנא tanna that says, so the גמרא gemara says, מאן תנא דכי
אמר הרי עלי מנחה מן השעורים יביא מן החיטים? man tanna deki
amar harei alai mincha min hase'orim yavi min hachittim?
Who is this תנא קמא? tanna kamma? Where do we find a
parallel to this תנא קמא tanna kamma idea that if you say
I'm going to bring a מנחה mincha from barley, you bring it
from wheat? We ignore the qualification which doesn't make sense. So אמר
חזקיה במחלוקת שנויה בית שמאי היא. amar Chizkiya bemachloket shnuya Beit Shammai
hi. This exactly parallels בית שמאי, Beit Shammai which is a very
nice interpretation. נזיר מן הגרוגרות, nazir min hagerogerot, ignore the גרוגרות, grogros,
you're a נזיר. nazir Okay, מנחה מן השעורים, mincha min hase'orim, ignore
the שעורים. se'orim. You said a מנחה. mincha. The second part doesn't
make sense and you ignore it. לאו אמר בית שמאי? lav amar
Beit Shammai? Doesn't בית שמאי Beit Shammai. say כי אמר מן הגרוגרות
ומן הדבלה הוי נזיר, ki amar min hagerogerot umin hadeveila havei nazir,
that you're a normal נזיר nazir and you ignore the second part
of the sentence? הכא נמי כי אמר מן השעורים, hacha nami ki
amar min hase'orim, if you say a מנחה mincha from שעורים, se'orim,
יביא מן החיטים. yavi min hachittim. You drop the שעורים se'orim which
is nonsense and you bring a normal מנחה. mincha. So this seems
to be a very nice parallel of our debate. Except it's weird
that you have a תנא קמא tanna kamma going like בית שמאי.
Beit Shammai. So let's see what the גמרא gemara says.
Sorry, but it doesn't seem parallel, right? It's the difference between throwing
out the whole thing and ignoring.
No,
both cases you bring the, you say מנחה מן השעורים mincha min
hase'orim and you bring a מנחה, mincha, right? נזיר מן הגרוגרות nazir
min hagerogerot and you're a נזיר, Nazir right? Okay, so the only
funny thing is that you'd have the תנא קמא tanna kamma going
according to בית שמאי. Beit Shammai. So the גמרא gemara says, but
that's the first opinion, yeah, that's the תנא קמא tanna kamma is
בית שמאי. Beis Shammai. You say a sentence, you basically accept upon
yourself something, נזירות, nezirus, מנחה, mincha, whatever. The qualifier at the end
which doesn't make sense is ignored. All right. So the גמרא Gemara
says, רבי יוחנן אמר, Rabbi Yochanan amar, רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan says,
אפילו תימא דברי הכל. afilu teima divrei hakol. No,
the תנא קמא tanna kamma there can be even בית הלל, Beit
Hillel. which would make sense because we rule like בית הלל. Beit
Hillel's So why is that different? Why are you obligated in a
מנחה mincha there? באומר, be'omer, person says, אילו הייתי יודע שאין נודרים
כך לא נדרתי כך אלא כך. ilu hayiti yode'a she'ein nodrim kach
lo nadarti kach ella kach.
Had I known that you couldn't bring a מנחה mincha from שעורים,
se'orim, I wouldn't have said שעורים, se'orim, I would have said חיטים.
chittim. Okay, which means now the question is does it have to
be באומר, be'omer, the guy actually said this, or is it כאומר?
ke'omer? We assume that a lot of people can confuse, oh I
didn't realize wheat, I thought barley, I didn't realize exactly how much,
I didn't realize this, I didn't realize that. It was an honest
mistake, but of course deep down I want to bring a מנחה.
mincha. The qualifier was just because I made some mistake, but that
wouldn't have, if I had realized that that wasn't possible, I would
have wanted to do a normal מנחה. mincha. As opposed to when
you actually say a נזיר Nazir from גרוגרות, grogros. nobody thinks there's
such a thing as a נזיר nazir. from גרוגרות, at least that's
our assumption. Okay, and maybe even if you said you did, we
wouldn't accept that claim. And therefore we say what you wanted to
do was to create some different type of a reality, a נזיר
Nazir from a גרוגרת. gerogeret. Fundamentally you wanted to be a נזיר,
Nazir. and this was some like mistaken qualifier.
Yeah. Haven't considered that there's other aspects to נזירות. Yeah. When you
say I'm a נזיר Nazir. from dates or whatever. Yep.
We're not considering that maybe you really wanted to be a נזיר
Nazir. טומאה tumah status, right? The shaving aspect, you know,
we're putting it all on the wine.
Right, could be.
I mean the מנחה mincha is kind of the same thing. There
are other הלכות halachot with other מנחה, mincha, right? Besides...
Yeah. Right.
So I'm surprised that the גמרא Gemara
doesn't explore that, I'm not sure in what way.
Yeah, I mean it is true that it all is. I mean
when it also said before about a person that tries to be
a נזיר nazir. from a little, he's a נזיר nazir from everything.
But was it all about the eating part and the wine part
or were there some examples that the person said I'm a נזיר
nazir from haircuts or something like that?
What was
that משנה? mishnah? הריני נזיר מן החרצנים ומן הזגים ומן התגלחת ומן
הטומאה. hareini nazir min hachartzanim umin hazaggim umin hatiglachat umin hatumah. So
there you had somebody that said I want to be a נזיר
just from טומאה tumah and everything comes on. But it is, so
you people, it is possible that they would focus on the other
aspects of נזירות. other things. But you are right, so much of
this emphasis is on is on the eating part of it. And
yeah, I don't know how that would play out here. So the
basic answer of the גמרא Gemara is that if you basically, if
it's an honest mistake, we can say that fundamentally you want to
bring a מנחה, mincha, and the other part was a mistake and
we ignore the mistake. The fundamental desire is to bring a מנחה.
mincha. Whereas if it wasn't, if really this wasn't like fundamentally you
wanted to be a נזיר but you got some specifics wrong, it
was a completely different concept that was going on here, then we
say then you didn't really accept נזירות. You had an idea that
נזירות was something fundamentally different than it actually was. Okay, and therefore
it's not binding. So the גמרא Gemara says like this,
okay, so that's the debate of רבי יוחנן Rabbi Yochanan and חזקיה.
Chizkiyah. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this, אמר חזקיה, amar
Chizkiyah, לא שנו אלא שאמר מן השעורים. lo shanu ella she-amar min
hase'orim.
So חזקיה Chizkiyah says this debate, remember חזקיה Chizkiyah said it was
the same debate בית הלל בית שמאי Beis Hillel Beis Shammai the
debate by the מנחה. mincha. And now he says this debate about
that you bring a מנחה mincha of when you said from barley
is only if you said from barley. אבל אמר מן העדשים, Avel
amar min ha-adashim, if you said I'm going to bring a מנחה
mincha from lentil beans, okay, לא מייתי ולא כלום. lo maysee v'lo
klum. Everybody would agree you don't bring anything. Why? Because that's sort
of like נזיר from גרוגרות. That's like a mistake that no normal
person makes. It's one thing to think barley or wheat, you didn't
think it's a big difference. But a מנחה mincha out of lentil
beans clearly is not the מנחה mincha in the תורה. Torah. Nobody
thinks that that's a possible מנחה, mincha, so you're trying to do
something completely new and therefore you're not obligating yourself. Okay? Got the
idea why that's different? It's not a sort of within the range
of normal mistakes people make and therefore we basically say you're trying
to do something completely different. Of course, as the גמרא Gemara says,
but that's רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's approach. רבי יוחנן's Rabbi Yochanan's approach
is it matters how big of a mistake you're making, how, you
know, how understandable of a mistake you're making. חזקיה Chizkiyah seems to
feel that we always ignore the end of your sentence. So the
גמרא Gemara says, מכדי, michdi, one minute, let's take a look. חזקיה
כמאן מוקים לה למתניתין. Chizkiyah k'man mokim lah lematnisin. Who does חזקיה
Chizkiyah say this idea about מנחה מן השעורים mincha min hase'orim was
going like? כבית שמאי, Ke-Beis Shammai, like בית שמאי. Beis Shammai's And
in בית שמאי's Beis Shammai case about נזיר מן הגרוגרות, nazir min
hagrogros, that was absurd. ועדשים לגבי מנחה כגרוגרות לגבי נזיר דמו. v'adashim
legabei mincha kegrogros legabei nazir damu. Lentil beans for a מנחה mincha
are like dates for a נזיר. Both of them are absurd, you
know, reframings of what the thing is. דקאמרי בית שמאי הוי נזיר.
D'ka-amrei Beis Shammai havei nazir. So but you, so בית שמאי Beis
Shammai, though says even when you say a נזיר from גרוגרות, which
is completely absurd, we ignore the גרוגרות. So if the position of
the מנחה mincha is following בית שמאי, Beis Shammai. מנחה מן העדשים
mincha min ha-adashim should also be a מנחה. mincha. We ignore the
end part of the sentence no matter how stupid it is. We
don't say you're fundamentally trying to do something different. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says,
so they'd have him bring the right thing.
Bring the right thing. We ignore the second part of your statement
which was nonsense. Right. Now it sounds like חזקיה Chizkiyah is admitting
that the only reason we say bring a מנחה mincha is because
it was within the normal realm and it was an understandable mistake.
But if you but if you were doing something radically different then
it's nonsense, is what he's saying. But that's not בית שמאי. Beis
Shammai בית שמאי Beis Shammai was radically different and we didn't say
it was nonsense. So the גמרא Gemara says ועדשים
לגבי מנחה כגרוגרות לגבי נזיר דמו. v'adashim legabei mincha kegrogros legabei nazir
damu. So הדר ביה חזקיה. hadar bei Chizkiyah. Alright, חזקיה Chizkiyah reversed
himself. He wound up siding with רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan. He wound
up saying that the only reason it works in the מנחה mincha
case is because it was a, you know, understandable mistake. But if
it's a radically different thing it won't work. So the גמרא Gemara
says, ואמאי הדר ביה, v'amyei hadar bei, why what made him reverse
himself? Why not stay with your position that no matter how stupid
the end is we drop it off? So the גמרא Gemara says,
אמר רבא, amar Rava, מתניתין קשיא ליה, masnisin kashya lei, because he
was bothered with that משנה mishna by the case of the מנחה.
mincha. מאי איריא דתני מן השעורים, Mai irya d'tani min hase'orim, why
did it only give the example about little mistakes when he said
barley? If you want to tell me that even a radically different
thing you still bring a מנחה, mincha, tell me that. ליתני מן
העדשים. Lisni min ha-adashim. Tell me even if you say a מנחה
mincha from lentil beans you still bring a מנחה. mincha. Since it
gave the example barley it shows that when you make small mistakes
we say that fundamentally you wanted to bring a מנחה mincha and
we drop the qualifier. But if you made a big mistake or
you said something way out of bounds then we would say you
were trying to do something completely different and it would not be
and it would not be binding. Okay? מאי איריא דתני מן השעורים
ליתני מן העדשים. Mai irya d'tani min hase'orim lisni min ha-adashim. אלא
סבר חזקיה, Ella savar Chizkiyah, so חזקיה Chizkiyah holds, כי אמרי בית
שמאי התם, ki amrei Beis Shammai hasam, כרבי יהודה. k'Rabbi Yehuda. Really
בית שמאי Beis Shammai, is going like רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, meaning,
I'm sorry, so בית שמאי, Beis Shammai I'm
sorry, so what's this? כי אמרי בית שמאי התם, ki amrei Beis
Shammai hasam, בית
שמאי Beit Shammai by what do you call it, by our משנה...
mishna...
oh I think the ראש Rosh takes this line out. This line
doesn't work. Hold on. Yeah this second
this line here doesn't doesn't work so well. Why are we introducing
רבי יהודה? Rebbi Yehuda? Because
what are we doing introducing רבי יהודה? Rebbi Yehuda? Oh, תוספות, תוספות
says it. דלא גריס הכא בסיפא כסבר חזקיה בית שמאי כרבי יהודה.
Dela goris hacha besaifa kasavar Chizkiyah Beit Shammai ke-Rebbi Yehuda. Okay. Why
do you have to introduce רבי יהודה Rebbi Yehuda here? בית שמאי
Beit Shammai holds what בית שמאי Beit Shammai always held, which is
that you drop the second half of the statement. But רבי יהודה
Rebbi Yehuda limits בית שמאי Beit Shammai to say you're a נזיר
מן הגרוגרות, Nazir min ha-grogrot, not that you're a נזיר. Why are
we introducing that? That's just confusing. תוספות takes out that whole line.
Okay, basically בית שמאי Beit Shammai, hold like we thought they did,
that you're a נזיר. You drop the second part of your statement.
You ignore the part that qualifies that doesn't make sense, okay? But
again, our משנה Mishna by the what do you call it? By
the מנחה, Mincha, that works now like בית שמאי, Beit Shammai that
works because it's a small mistake and it's an understandable mistake. And
we say bottom line you still wanted to bring a מנחה. Mincha.
So now we have חזקיה Chizkiyah going like רבי יוחנן, Rebbi Yochanan,
okay? בית שמאי Beit Shammai. says no matter how stupid the second
part of your statement is, how much you tried to do something
radically different, you're bound by the first part of your statement and
you're a נזיר. Okay, whereas the תנא קמא Tanna Kamma by the
case of the מנחה Mincha says look, since you said something that
was only a little bit off, we say fundamentally you wanted to
bring a מנחה Mincha and the other part was a mistake that
we're going to ignore. Okay, whereas if you say something radically off,
then we say you're trying to do something radically different and it's
not binding. Alright, so that makes it all work even within בית
הלל. Beis Hillel In our case of the משנה, Mishna, of נזיר
מן הגרוגרות Nazir min ha-grogrot is radically off and it's not binding.
But if it's only a little bit off, it would be binding.
Okay, yeah?
So radically off and not binding is very different from not being.
Right, and that's like yeah exactly, exactly.
אינו מוציא דבריו לבטלה. Eino motzi devarav levatala. And that's what I
was trying to say before. אינו מוציא דבריו לבטלה Eino motzi devarav
levatala is not, yeah it means like we don't give it הלכה
Halacha meaning a הלכה Halacha binding thing, exactly, or we do, we
insist that it does have הלכה Halacha binding thing. Okay, so now
it goes like this: רבי יוחנן אמר, Rebbi Yochanan amar,
so that's חזקיה. Chizkiyah. חזקיה Chizkiyah wound up coming around to רבי
יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan that when you say something radically off it's nothing,
that's בית הלל's Beis Hillel, approach in our משנה. Mishna. When you
say something a little bit off, then we ignore the mistake and
it's still binding and that's the position about the מנחה. Mincha. רבי
יוחנן אמר, Rebbi Yochanan amar, אפילו מן העדשים, Afilu min ha-adashim,
that even, even if you say in our in the משנה Mishna
by מנחה, Mincha, a מנחה מן העדשים, Mincha min ha-adashim, you're still
going to have to bring a מנחה. Mincha. So everybody is now
switching sides because רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan was the one that started
by saying that it works only because you made an understandable mistake.
So the גמרא says והא רבי יוחנן הוא דאמר באומר אילו הייתי
יודע שאין נודרין כך לא נדרתי כך אלא כך? Ve-ha Rebbi Yochanan
hu de-amar be-omer ilu hayiti yodeah she-ein nodrin kach lo nadarti kach
ela kach? One minute, רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is the one who
says that the reason it's binding in the case of the מנחה
Mincha is because you say, one minute, oh I didn't realize you
couldn't bring that way, had I known I wouldn't have said it,
meaning it was an understandable mistake. So according to רבי יוחנן Rebbi
Yochanan when you say מן העדשים, Min ha-adashim, it shouldn't be binding
because it's not an understandable mistake.
It should not.
It should not. So why does he say it is? So the
גמרא says לדבריו דחזקיה הוא דקאמר. Lidvarav de-Chizkiyah hu de-ka'amar.
He's saying it according to you חזקיה. Chizkiyah. את, meaning to me,
according to what רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan is saying: Look, I understand,
I say the only reason it's binding in the case of the
מנחה Mincha is because you were only a little bit off and
it was an understandable mistake. But according to you חזקיה, Chizkiyah, you
should say even if it's a big mistake it should be binding.
Why?
הוא דקאמר. Hu de-ka'amar. את מאי טעמא קהדרת בך? At mai ta'ama
ka-hadartat bach? Why did you reverse yourself and say that when you
make a big mistake it's not binding? משום דלא קתני מן העדשים
Mishum dela katani min ha-adashim
because the משנה Mishna didn't give the more radical example of lentil
beans. It only gave the slight mistake of barley. So you that
led you חזקיה Chizkiyah to come along to come around to my
position that if you make a small mistake it's binding and a
big mistake it's not. So דילמא, Dilma, one minute, you shouldn't reverse
yourself. You should stick to your guns. דילמא לא מיבעיא קאמר, Dilma
lo mibaya ka'amar, maybe the משנה Mishna says it goes without saying.
לא מיבעיא קאמר מן העדשים דמייתי מנחה מעליא. Lo mibaya ka'amar min
ha-adashim de-mayiti Mincha ma'alya.
If you make a big mistake and you say מן העדשים, Min
ha-adashim, maybe that's even more obvious it's binding. Why? דאיכא למימר מהדר
הוא דהדר ביה, De-ika lemeimar mehadur hu dehadar bei, and תפוס לשון
ראשון Tfos lashon rishon like we were saying before according to one
approach of בית שמאי. Beis Shammai, Then מן העדשים Min ha-adashim is
clearly a reversal because that's an idiotic thing to say so clearly
it must be just because you changed your mind. And that's why
maybe that's clearly binding because you can't reverse yourself and you're stuck
with your first statement. אלא כי אמר מן השעורים ודאי הכי קאמר.
Ela ki amar min ha-se'orim vadai hachi ka'amar.
But when he said שעורים, Se'orim, he's not reversing himself. He really
thinks that there is something like this, a מנחה מן השעורים. Mincha
min ha-se'orim. Maybe that's the only thing he wants to bring. It's
not a reversal, it's his intention. But maybe he wanted only this
way. אי כמנחת עומר קאמר או כמנחת סוטה תקדש. Ei ke-Minchat Omer
ka'amar o ke-Minchat Sotah tikdash.
If I can bring something like a מנחת עומר Minchat Omer or
a מנחת סוטה Minchat Sotah which is out of barley. then I
want to bring it. אי לאו לא, ee lo lo, and if
not I don't want to bring it. I don't say fundamentally I
want to bring a מנחה. mincha. No, I only want to bring
a מנחה mincha out of שעורים. seorim. קמשמע לן דמייתי מן החיטין,
kamashma lan d'mayti min hachittin, and that's why it's telling you you
bring from חיטין. chittin. So what does it tell you in the
end? It's saying in a way this is echoing back the beginning
of the סוגיא, sugya, which is if somebody makes a big mistake,
they're really off at the end, we have two ways of going.
One way of going is you're so off that you were trying
to do something totally new. You can't do something totally new and
it's not binding, right? So that's what sort of חזקיה Chizkia would
say, even the approach by מנחה mincha that it is when you're
a little off, when you're big off you're trying to do something
completely new it's not binding and that's בית הלל Beis Hillel by
the נזיר. But the other approach is no, when you're trying to
do something totally off, that shows that you're trying to reverse yourself
and it's too late to reverse yourself, and if it's too late
to reverse yourself you're bound by it, right? And that was one
approach according to בית שמאי, Beis Shammai? that the reason they bound
you was because it was too late to reverse yourself. Okay, so
we have these different possible meanings but bottom line is is that
in the case by the מנחה, mincha,
everybody,
presumably that works even according to בית הלל, Beis Hillel right? Because
why would you have a תנא קמא Tanna Kamma there be like
בית שמאי? Beis Shammai So presumably there when you made a little
bit of a mistake, you still can say okay but fundamentally you
wanted to bring a מנחה, mincha, this is חזקיה's Chizkia approach, so
the little bit of a mistake doesn't disqualify the whole sentence, we'll
put it down to a mistake and it somehow won't redefine what
you were doing. Okay, but if you did some tried to do
something like radically different, okay, you said מן השעורה min haseora or
you said נזיר מן הגרוגרות, nazir min hagogros,
so there בית הלל says well that's totally off and it's nothing,
and בית שמאי Beis Shammai says well maybe either just like the
other thing is we just ignore it or B we say you
were trying to reverse yourself and you're still stuck with the first
thing that you said, right? And that's בית שמאי Beis Shammai that
says that you're bound by it. Okay, so lot of different possibilities
but bottom line here is is that we have a question about
what to do when you say the something a little bit off
whereas בית שמאי is much more prepared to sort of trap you
into the נזירות, you said the word נזיר it's going to be
hard to get yourself out of that and בית הלל is much
more willing to look at the whole sentence and say that look
bottom line it doesn't look like you were trying to be a
normal נזיר so you're not going to be bound by it.
All right.